I would like to share with you all the time.
You can realize that, don't you?
There was unbelievable confusion.
There was anxiety.
There was worry.
Here's the context.
They had followed Jesus for three years.
They had given up their businesses.
Some of them, it seems as though they got to see themselves very little.
They had given all and everything for this mission, this vision, this man who's going to redeem Israel.
They've torn all of them.
They've watched him do the miraculous over and over and over and over again.
And then, just a few days before his resurrection, they watched the gruesome torture of their leader who they expected to deliver Israel from the dead.
And the Scriptures call us that they did not understand from the Scriptures that he was to rise again from the dead.
They were convinced he was going to deliver them.
And they watched him torture them.
And so you find the disciples confused and fearful behind lost doors.
Has anyone ever had a vision by?
And I'm talking about something that you were sure was what your life was about.
Your plan, your life, your dream, your vision, your cause, your hope, your purpose, your identity.
You know, the paradigm, the aspect of God giving a vision, and then watching, destroying the vision, and then watching the vision die.
And then God reverently from the dead is a meta-narrative that goes throughout the Scriptures.
You see it everywhere.
Abraham, Abraham, leave your country.
Go to a country I'm going to give you, a land I'm going to give you, and you're going to become the father of many nations.
And so, as a young man, he leaves, and his wife, and those who are with him, but he has no kids.
Do you know when he got to the promised land at the end of his life, the only piece of property he actually owned in the land that God had promised him was his wife's grave.
He was a hundred years old, I'm going to be the father of nations, and he has no kids.
When it was announced to him and his wife, his wife lost, he was 90 years old.
He had this incredible victory from God, he pursued the vision, and from all practical purposes he died, and actually for him twice.
Because then God re-washed us, re-apened her womb, and she had this son, and then God says, "Okay, I want you to talk to him."
He's here with Joseph.
Joseph, early on, he has a vision from God, and it's a correct vision.
God gives him the vision.
His problem was not the accuracy of his vision, his problem was the timing of his vision.
And so he ran to all of his brothers and sisters, he ran to his mom and dad, and had a dream from the Lord,
and in the dream you all bow down to me, and I'm going to rule.
And how well do you think that went over?
He ends up in the ditch, he gets out of the ditch and sold into slavery,
and he spends 40 years in a foreign country often for doing the right thing in jail.
And then God brought it back to life.
Moses tried to deliver his people and ended up out in the wilderness.
David, King David, you're going to be king, you're going to be anointed king, and he becomes the generalist of Saul,
and Saul becomes his father-in-law.
He seems to be doing it, and next thing you know he's in a cave hiding from his father-in-law,
he's trying to kill him.
There is this many narrative of God gives a vision, we go and we pursue that vision, and the vision dies.
And then God brought it back to life.
Moses tried to deliver his people and ended up out in the wilderness.
David, King David, you're going to be king, you're going to be anointed king,
and he becomes the generalist of Saul, and Saul becomes his father-in-law.
He seems to be doing it, and next thing you know he's in a cave hiding from his father-in-law who's trying to kill him.
There is this many narrative of God gives a vision, we go and we pursue that vision, and the vision dies.
So that God can resurrect it from the dead, so he gets the glory, not us, but God.
And so here is the meta-vision, the meta-narrative being worked out in the extreme.
The front of God has called his king, and they have preached and they have done the miraculous.
And then they watched him literally die of tortuous griefs and this.
You know, my first church, I was wrong, I was naive, didn't know what I was doing,
and I just thought if you preach hard enough and pray hard enough, God will grow the church.
The first year it worked, the church doubled, and then the core people in the church
chased everyone that we had reached for the Lord enough.
And I had no clue what was going on, I was done, I was naive, and so I thought,
"Oh, I just gotta preach harder, I just gotta pray harder, I just gotta work harder."
And although I've paid $4,000 a year, I've given about 60, 70 hours a week
because it was God's call in my life, and I must pursue it.
Until I got this place where I'm in my bed and checked it out at 10 o'clock in the morning
because I'm going through clinical depression.
Because I'm watching my pursuit of my vision go.
I must tell you that it was out of that that God rebirthed a new concept of church and church planting,
and I had the privilege of being part of the most amazing church plant I've ever been a part of,
and it was God, because I was done.
It was like God said, "Okay, Matt, I see what you can do.
Are you interested in looking away at it?"
Are you interested in looking away at it?
I'm interested in looking away at it.
And he just said, "Don't tell anyone."
And I listened to him until I got so afraid
that once my mom found out and I hadn't told her,
I was getting in twice as much trouble,
and so I didn't tell and then I went and told her.
Are you identifying with what I'm saying here?
So that's what's going on with these women.
In the Gospel of Mark, it records that they went there
and they got so scared at the event that they told no one.
And we find out later from Matthew and from Luke
that they in fact did go and they did tell,
they did obey, they did follow.
But again, there is this unbelievable belief.
It's confusion.
There's worry.
And it's true that the parameters of Jesus
were pretty used to confusion.
You know, Jesus walked on water
and they thought he was a ghost.
Jesus would speak, and sometimes he'd speak in parables
and they'd just come out.
I'm not quite sure what he said.
It's just ahead.
Jesus said at one point in the Gospel of John,
"Unless you eat my body and drink my blood,
you can have no part in me."
He didn't explain what he meant by that.
We know now that he's talking about communion.
And then we understand that.
And after the disciples at the time, crowds of people left.
And the disciples went to the Lord and they said,
"Lord, that's a pretty hard stone."
And he doesn't answer their question.
He just looks at them and says, "So are you going to leave me too?"
And their response was, and here's my interpretation of it.
"You know, we're actually thinking about it, Lord, but where should we go?"
"You know the words of life."
"I don't understand, Lord. It makes no sense, but you are obviously Lord."
And so they were used to be confusing, but not at this category.
This is categorically different.
Because their whole potency of identity was ramped up in something that was now ripped from them.
Okay.
So let's get into John, go to the next slide,
and let me read for you the first two verses.
"Early on the first day of the week, while it was still dark,
Mary Magdalene went to the tomb and saw that the stone had been removed from the entrance.
So she came running to Simon Peter and the other disciple,
and the one Jesus loved, and said,
"They've taken the Lord out of the tomb, and we do not know where they have put him."
I remember with you, folks, that Matthew, Mark, and Luke were written much earlier in the Gospel of John.
The synoptic Gospels were written somewhat around the same time,
but the Gospel of John was written much later.
We believe that John has yet access to Matthew, Mark, and Luke,
that he had those accounts.
And he's like, "Yeah, those accounts are good, but there's more that you need to know."
And so he tells us a lot of things that we wouldn't know about from Matthew, Mark, and Luke,
because he read them and goes, "That's good, but let me tell you more of the story."
And so he's giving an understanding of actually the timeline here.
She goes there very early in the morning, and she gets there, and the door is open.
We assume from the other Gospels, she's left in, she's not there, and so she raises it.
She's fearful. She makes it serious.
By the way, if he is the Mary, Martha's sister,
she's actually experienced the resurrection the months before her brother, remember?
And yet, if any of you like this, that does this miracle, and three weeks later,
you don't think he can do the next miracle?
Anyone else identify with him?
He delivers you, and a month and a half later, "Oh, oh, oh, mommy!
Are you doing it? Are you getting so real good?"
Well, she doesn't think about that resurrection.
Maybe it wasn't her. I don't know.
Depends on tradition.
But as far as she's concerned, their mission is over.
Perhaps her life is over.
She's dead.
And listen to what they say.
Um, according to the next slide.
Oh, back up one.
Oh, okay, this is what I want.
Uh, they have taken the what?
She is in the midst of confusion, the midst of fear, the midst of uncertainty.
She doesn't know where this is going to end up.
As far as she's concerned, it's over.
And yet, somehow in the midst of that uncertainty, she's still there.
So here's, here's point number one for today.
When you are in the midst of debilitating worry, anxiety, or fear.
Number one, next slide.
Acknowledge it.
Acknowledge that his lordship does not depend on your understanding of the circumstances.
That goes back to the, you know, "Lord, I believe, help my unbelief."
"Lord, I don't understand what you're doing, but I understand that you are good."
You do know that God is always good, but all of his goodness doesn't always feel good.
His plans are not our plans.
His ways are not our ways.
The things that he sees that we, that we, that we're calling us on.
And so, Mary, in this time of unbelievable fear and anxiety, still calls him the Lord.
So, most importantly, at that time, if someone that you loved died, you would, you would visit the tomb for three days.
The Jews believed that by the fourth day, the spirit had departed.
And, and that's why, by the way, with Lazarus, he was raised in the fourth day to raise him from the dead just to show that he can do anything.
But, but in their culture, for three days, he would go to the tomb of the one that you loved and you would mourn and you weep.
And in Mary's context, she was prohibited from doing that on the first day because it was a Sabbath.
And on the Sabbath, she couldn't go.
And so, at the early, while it was still done, at the earliest possible moment, she went.
It's really, any of you think I almost remember the, the TV show, The Good Wife?
Here's the other TV show.
I don't remember The Good Wife.
Okay.
Oh, there was one scene in it where, this, this, this woman, who has a, a husband, who's a politician.
He keeps on her.
He ends up in jail.
He comes to his faithful.
She has to go back into law.
And, and she's feeling the stresses of law and how hard it is and she starts to drink more.
And there's this one scene where she stays at the table.
There's a wine bottle.
And there's a cup.
And the clock says 4:55.
And she's waiting for 5 o'clock.
Mary is just waiting for she can grow and, and, and, grieve, mourn.
We embarked to say this way, go to the next slide.
Her one desire was to reap her loss over Jesus' dead body.
She had delivered her from seven days.
She'd like this one.
She was her Lord.
You know, the Scriptures say, "To whom much is forgiving, so they love much."
There's something about when God does this amazing thing for you.
That it just, "To whom much is forgiving, so they love much."
This is Mary.
Go to the next slide.
Then the disciples went back to her home.
So, so she goes to the disciples.
They come running down in the story of, in, in John.
And, and John runs ahead.
He gets there.
He stops.
He looks in.
Peter finally catches up.
Peter runs on in.
And it seems that the Jesus is not there.
Mary finally gets there.
She's, I mean, she's already gone all the way back to get him.
And now she's coming back again.
So she went there.
He went back.
She's fine.
So she gets there a little bit later.
And then she gets there.
They're like, "Okay, well, I, I, he's, he's, he's making it."
John, he says, believed.
He didn't understand yet, but he believed.
He believed the resurrection, even though he didn't understand that.
Of course, he said, predicted that that would be the case.
But Peter didn't, didn't believe.
And so she stays there.
She looks on in.
And she sees these, these two angels.
And these two angels speak to her.
They say, "Why are you looking for the, the living here?
Who are you looking for?"
She says, "My Lord."
And in the midst of that, there's someone outside.
And you ask for what's going on.
And it's actually Jesus that's keeping such grief.
She doesn't even recognize him.
She thinks he's the gardener.
And so she says, "If you're the gardener, if you, if you've taken it, please, please tell
me where you've put my Lord.
Tell me where you've put my Lord.
Tell me where he's going."
Then the disciple went back to the home.
But Mary stood outside and became quiet.
And she said, "If you're the gardener, if you've taken it, please, tell me where you've
put my Lord.
Tell me where he's going."
Then the disciple went back to the home.
But Mary stood outside and became quiet.
And she said, "And in the midst of that, there's someone outside who's asked for what's
going on."
And it's actually Jesus that's keeping such grief.
She doesn't even recognize him.
She thinks he's the gardener.
And so she says, "If you're the gardener, if you've taken it, please, please tell me where
you've put my Lord.
Tell me where he's going."
Then the disciple went back to the home.
But Mary stood outside and became quiet.
As far as she's carried him away, "Tell me where you've put him, and I'll go get him."
So what do you do when you're worried or afraid, first of all, of knowledge that his Lordship
does not depend on your understanding of the circumstances?
I want you to come to the next slide.
Let love motivate you, even if you're confused and furious.
Mary was responding to her love so far in the world, even if she had no clue what was going on.
But she has this conversation with him that's short.
She's not looking for him.
She's looking in the mirror wondering where he is.
And that's why Jesus said to her, "Mary."
And at the hearing of her name from the voice of her Lord, she turned and swaddled and said,
"Rabody!
Teacher!"
She all of a sudden understood, "This is the resurrected Jesus."
By the way, I find it fascinating in a culture that demeaned women, God chose a woman to be
the first one to witness the resurrection of the Lord and Savior.
If you want an affirmation of women, right there is a good one.
It's an awesome one.
So number three, "What should I do when I'm worried or afraid?"
Next slide.
I don't think you just hear the Lord's voice that he speaks.
Coach, I don't know what to do on those hills.
I don't know what loss he's having.
I don't know what pain he's struggling with.
I know that they're here.
I know there's significant ones.
I was speaking with someone of just this week who lost a job that his comment was,
and choose to trust Jesus.
He's been faithful in the past and he'll choose to trust Jesus.
In other words, trust doesn't come naturally here.
But I know he's faithful.
And so I make a choice to choose him and to choose to believe.
But in the midst of your choosing, point number three, "What do I do when I'm fear or when I'm worried?"
How does anybody hear the Lord's voice if he speaks?
I think that there are many times when God is talking and we're busy doing something else.
My children, my son, when he would talk to me, if I was busy doing something and he couldn't get my attention,
he'd finally go, "Do you understand that?"
And I go, "Huh?"
Have an ear.
Have an ear to hear.
Because sometimes the Lord is already talking.
In fact, I think sometimes we say, "Talk to me, Lord."
And what we really mean by that is, "Lord, I don't like what I'm already hearing.
Tell me something different."
If the Lord speaks, have an ear to hear.
Okay, let's jump down to John 20:17-18.
When Jesus was there, she says, "Rabboni."
Apparently she goes and she grabs him and she doesn't want him.
And Jesus said, "Hey, don't hold on to me.
I haven't yet gone to my father.
I need to ascend."
And there's a whole lot of scholarly debate about exactly what's happening there.
I just take it pretty straightforward.
She's so amazed at the Lord and she just goes.
He's like, "Oh, okay, hold on, you know.
Stop holding me."
And then he tells her, "Because I need a job for you.
I want you to go and tell the disciples that I've heard he's needed."
And that's exactly what she does.
You know, we want you to focus on the news.
This is the news.
Next slide.
This is really the fourth point.
This is definitely the news.
Okay.
I love the story of a new pastor who preached the message.
He asked the words that once said, "Oh, Pastor, thank you.
That was a great message."
And the next week, when he got up to 60, that's the same message.
And everyone thought, "Well, the guy is 60 years old.
You know, maybe he's getting a little old."
And so they were gracious.
And there was still, you know, it was back in the days when you spoke at the gospel door
and you greeted everyone who walked out.
You know, "Good message, Pastor.
Good message, Pastor.
Good message, Pastor."
And the third week, he preached the same message.
And so someone had their guns in the way out and said, "Oh, Pastor, that's a good message,
but we heard that one's third three times done.
He said, "Well, when you start doing this one, I'll give you another one."
But I think sometimes we thank the Lord.
We want revelation, and He wants obedience.
We want insight, and He wants obedience.
I used to tell my kids all the time, "Why?"
You know, kids, "Why do I have to do that? Why? Why? Why?"
And 90% of the time, the "Why" was not a real lie.
It was the versionary topic.
And I used to tell my kids, "Tell you what?
After you do this, I'll tell you why."
Because obedience really needs to precede understanding.
That's very true if you have little kids.
You know, don't put the paper clip into that electrical outlet.
Why? Just don't do it.
And once you get obedience, then you can tell them why.
I think that's what it is that the Lord something is.
He wants to teach you.
He wants obedience.
So what should I do when I'm afraid?
That's fine.
What should I do when I'm afraid?
What I'd like to do with you, because I'm convinced that while God chooses the forces of preaching to stay with them in the community,
that real transformation does not come from fear anymore.
But it comes from doing.
I mean, I -- you can watch a video on an exercise program, and it's not going to do any good unless you get up and do the video.
You can read about a diet, but it's not effective unless you're actually doing something.
And so, too, with spiritual growth.
God wants to grow you.
He wants to help you overcome worry and fear.
But hearing about it will never do.
You know, the Scriptures say perfect love can't set all fear.
And so I have friends who say, well, you need to memorize that Scripture where it is.
Here's the problem.
It doesn't say memorizing perfect love can't set all fear, can't set all fear.
Perfect love is actually an encounter.
It's an episodic encounter.
And so, I'm convinced that as much as possible -- and I think Ryan and I share this as we've walked through the various activities you try to have of your response to the preaching of the word,
whether it's communion or whether it's a prayer, whether it's an activity, whether it's going out and serving when we talk about service,
that somehow, it's when you engage, when you do, that God meets you, and God begins to translate your anger.
And so I'd like to teach you the prayer of redemption, an old practice, an ancient practice.
It will be broken down into four steps.
And it really comes down to the fact that you're not God, He is.
That your ways are not His ways.
That your understanding is not His understanding.
That He is good even though He doesn't feel good.
It's this act of actually dealing with the worry and the fear.
So if we can just take about four or five minutes, and I'm going to give you four steps in the prayer of elanquishment, and I'm going to encourage you to actually do them here.
If you want us to get up to anywhere, you want the sins of anyone else.
I'm not going to make you feel uncomfortable.
If God makes you feel uncomfortable, that's His job.
He can do that.
But I'd like you to engage.
Because my hope is that various practices we teach you, you can engage in a regular basis without transformation.
It comes by positioning those thoughts before God's issues in our lives.
I don't want you to live in the fear and worry of the anxiety.
So, some of you probably already have a situation in your mind.
It might be something really simple, like, "I'm losing out of my hair and I don't want to look so bad."
Or it might be something dramatic, as my kids have really gone sad.
"I'm now just falling apart."
"My job is unlisted."
"What I thought you would call me to do, I'm no longer here."
I would encourage you, by the way, this week, to actually make a risk of seven or eight things.
And walk through the care of elanquishment.
And let's do this.
If you'll close your eyes.
Father, I pray for the many women here.
We welcome your spirit.
We ask that by your spirit, you would introduce us into a way of encountering your goodness.
And finding deliverance in the midst of our own fear and worries.
If you look in your eyes, step number one.
In prayer, admit to God that what you fear might help you.
If you look in your eyes, we're not in control.
We have influence.
We can impact.
But we're not in control.
Control is a superpower.
Now, this is not advocation.
It's not spaderism.
You have influence.
And let me excuse you to say, "I have no influence.
I can do nothing."
That's not what we're saying here.
But this is acknowledging before God.
That while you're always good, your ways are not my ways.
While you're always good, I don't always perceive that it's good at the moment.
This is an act of not looking at the surgeon's hands, but looking at the surgeon's eyes.
Because he loves you.
He cares about you.
So I'd like you to take 30 seconds, and whatever that fear or anxiety is, just before God, in prayer, admit to what you feel.
Amen.
Step number two.
Verbally to God, whether it's verbally in your heart or out loud, place the situation in God's name.
This is where we say, "I choose to believe."
God, I give this to you.
By the way, this is really a warning from God's name.
This is kind of like nine every morning.
It's a real debilitating anxiety of fear.
Because God doesn't act like a vending machine.
But he does lose.
So I'd like you to just take 30 seconds and tell the Lord, "What do you want to mean?"
You're placing this situation in his, loving, and faith in his.
You're placing this situation in his.
Step number three.
Pleasing that you will expect whatever feeling is.
Folks, it's easier to relinquish input goals than action goals.
I'm sure there wasn't a single disciple that thought Jesus dying on the cross
as a good idea to come.
Not one.
Again, this is not giving up.
It's not saying that you won't work towards the good that you know.
But he is letting go of your own self-destruction that somehow you are their sovereign.
That you are in charge.
It is an ultimate that he is good.
Lord, whatever you are, in it you are good.
You are sovereign, and you are good.
And I will accept it.
If you take 30 seconds, relative to whatever the issue is for you,
and tell him that you will accept whatever grace is.
This is Father the Father's son.
Job said, "Though he's blaming, yet will I further him."
The Hebrew children said, "That he will rescue us, but even if he doesn't, we will not worship your idol."
Step four.
In your heart of hearts, acknowledge that his plans, whatever they are, his plans, they are always better than yours.
He has something good in it.
Because he is good.
He is good.
And he is good to you.
So take 30 seconds and just acknowledge to God that his plans are always better than yours.
Thank you.
Father, I pray that whatever work you've done with your children here this morning, for whomever has engaged and sought you, and pray for relinquishment, I pray in Jesus' name that you would, at the power of your Holy Spirit, feel the work that you are doing.
That in perfect love, in our experience of perfect love with you, that I feel would be helpful.
He believes your work.
Spear your work now for your kingdom's faith and for the benefit of your children.
Amen.
And now unto him who is able to keep you, and to cause you to stand before his presence, blameless and what was great for him.
To the only wise God, our service, and Jesus Christ, our Lord, be glory, and majesty, dominion, and power, based now and for the Lord.
Go in his mercy and his admonition.
Amen.